It was a small town by a small river and a small lake.
小さな川と小さな湖に囲まれた小さな町でした。
In a small northern part of a Midwest state.
中西部の州の北がわの小さな地域です。
There wasn't so much wilderness around
そこにはあまり自然がありませんでした。
that you couldn't see the town.
町を見ることができませんでした。
On the other hand, there wasn't so much town around
いっぽうで、周囲に町があまりなく
that you couldn't see and feel and touch the wilderness.
大自然を見たり感じたりふれたりできなかったのです。
And the town was full of fences to walk on
そして町には歩くためのフェンスや、
and sidewalks to skate on.
スケートできる歩道もたくさんありました。
And the muted cries and laughter of boys and girls.
そして少年少女たちのしずかなさけび声と笑い声。
Full of costumes, dreams and pumpkin spirits
いしょうや夢やカボチャのせいれいでいっぱい
preparing for the greatest night of the year.
一年で一番の夜にむけてじゅんびしています。
Better than Easter, better than Christmas.
イースターよりも、クリスマスよりも楽しいんです。
Halloween.
ハロウィン。
'Jenny, you're gonna raise the dead'
『ジェニー、あんなにさわがしいと死者を』
'with all that racket down there.'
『よみがえらせることになるよ。』
'Just looking for another broom, mom.'
『ただ別のほうきを探してるだけだよ、ママ。』
'You can always… use the new vacuum cleaner.'
『まぁ…新しいそうじきを使えるよ』
Ha ha, very funny.
はは、すごく面白いね。
Pip is really gonna love this.
ピップは本当にこれが大好きになるよ。
'A little more on my own. There. That's it.'
『もう少し自分でやってみる。ここで。それだけだ』
'Oh, yeah, by the way, dad..'
『あ、そうだ、ところでお父さん…』
'Sorry about using up all your gauze.'
『ガーゼを全部使っちゃってごめんね』
It's okay, Ralph.
大丈夫だよ、ラルフ。
I-I just hope no one needs any first aid, tonight.
今夜は誰も応急処置が必要にならないといいな…
Or you have to go to the bathroom anytime soon.
それともすぐにトイレに行かないといけないとかね。
Gotta go, can't keep Pip waiting.
行かないと、ピップを待たせられないよ。
Yeah. Bet it'll even scare Pip.
うん。ピップさえびっくりさせられるかもね。
'Tom Skeleton, you're one lucky boy.'
『トム・スケルトン、君はラッキーな子だね』
A name like Skelton on this kinda night.
こんな夜に「スケルトン」って名前はぴったりだ。
Uh-oh. Oh, Pip's gonna kill me for being late.
あぁ、遅れたせいでピップに怒られそうだ。
Woo!
わーい！
'Trick-or-treat!'
『トリック・オア・トリート』
Trick-or-treat!
トリック・オア・トリート!
- Yeah.
- Ha ha ha.
- うん。
- ははは。
- Alright, we made it.
- It's gonna be great.
- よし、たどり着いたね。
- すごく楽しくなるよ。
I'm ready for the treats.
お菓子をもらう準備ができたよ。
But I get more candy than you do, Wally.
でも僕は君よりたくさんキャンディをもらえるんだ、ウォリー。
- You and who else?
- Take that back.
- あなたと他に誰？
- 言い直して。
- Come on, Wally.
- Hey, you guys, stop it.
- さあ、ウォリー。
- ねえ、みんな、やめてよ。
Wait, where's Pip?
待って、ピップはどこ？
He's never been late for a Halloween
ハロウィンで遅れたことがないんだ
in a million zillion years.
何百万年、何十億年もの間だよ。
- Bet its some kinda trick.
- Sure it is.
- きっと何かのトリックだね。
- もちろんだよ。
For once, let's surprise him.
たまには彼を驚かせよう。
Come on.
さあ。
Pip!
ピップ！
Ah, yes, Joe Pipkin.
ああ、そうだね、ジョー・ピプキン。
Some say, that on the day he was born
ある人は言う、彼が生まれたその日、
all the soda pop bottles in the world fizzed over.
世界中のソーダ瓶がすべて泡を吹き出したと。
Pipkin, who could yell louder, sing better
ピプキンは、だれよりも大声でさけべ、だれよりも上手に歌え、
and eat more popcorn.
だれよりも多くのポップコーンを食べられる人だ。
Pip, the greatest boy who ever lived.
ピップ、今までで最も偉大な少年だ。
There's his house.
そこが彼の家だ。
- Huh?
- Impossible.
- えっ？
- ありえない。
It can't be.
まさか。
What?
どうしたの？
'Where are the jack-o-lanterns?'
『ジャック・オー・ランタンはどこにあるの？』
And the corn shocks on the porch.
そしてげんかん先にトウモロコシのいなほがゆれている。
'And monsters clinging to the roof.'
『やねにしがみついているモンスターはどこ?』
Something's wrong, awfully wrong.
何かがおかしい、とても変だ。
Oh, Pip.
ああ、ピップ。
Hey, Tom, look at that.
ねえ、トム、あれ見て。
'Oh, my gosh, it's a note.'
『なんてこった、メモだ！』
'What's it say?'
『何が書いてあるの？』
"Dear Tom, and all the gang, didn't mean to spoil
「トムとみんなへ、台無しにするつもりはなかったんだ
your Halloween. Off to the hospital.
ハロウィンのことだよ。びょういんへ行くんだ。
Something about appendicitis, don't worry."
何だかちゅうすいえんのこと、でも安心して。」
'Signed, Pip.'
『ピップより』
Appendicitis?
ちゅうすいえん？
You can die from that, right?
それで死ぬこともあるんだよね？
"P.S.
「追伸
Go ahead without me, I'll catch up. Ready, set, go."
私ぬきですすんで。すぐにおいつくから。よーい、スタート！」
But we can't start Halloween without Pip.
でもピップがいないとハロウィンは始められない。
It wouldn't be official.
正式なものにならない。
There's a shortcut to the hospital.
病院への近道があるよ。
Not, tha-that shortcut.
あっ あの近道じゃないでくれ。
Come on, you all heard him. Ready, set, go!
さあ、みんなは彼が聞こえたでしょ。よーい、スタート！
Think Pip's gonna be surprised, Tom?
ピップはおどろくだろうと思うかい、トム？
He did say to start Halloween without him.
彼はピップなしでハロウィンを始めようと言ったよね。
It'll be worth it to see the look on his face.
彼のかおを見ると、やって良かったと思えるよ。
Woodside, comin' through.
ウッドサイド、行くよ。
Jenny, wait. Stop. Wait up.
ジェニー、待って。止まって。もう少し待って。
Oh!
あっ！
There. There's the shortcut.
そこだ。ちかみちが見つかった。
'Not the ravine.'
たにぞこいがいでお願い。
Eh, got any other shortcuts to choose from, Tom?
あの、ほかにえらべるちかみちはあるの？トム？
Ralph does have a point there.
ラルフの言うこと、たしかに。
I think.
たしかに。
What did I tell you? Look.
何て言ったか覚えてる？見て。
'It's Pip. Pip!'
『ピップだぞ、ピップ！』
Hey, I-I can see right through him.
ねぇ、彼の中まで見えるよ。
Nah, it's just this funny moonlight.
いや、ただこのへんな月ひかりだよ。
The important thing is, he isn't sick.
大事なのは、彼はびょうきじゃないことだ。
But what about the hospital?
でもびょういんはどうするの？
Don't you get it? It was a joke all the time.
分かんないの？ずっといたずらだったんだよ。
The ambulance, that note on the door.
きゅうきゅうしゃ、ドアにつけってあったメモ。
What a trickster. Hey, Pip!
なんていたずら者だ。おぉい、ピップ！
You sure had us fooled!
本当にだまされたよ！
Where's your Halloween costume?
ハロウィンのかそうは？
'Hey, Pip, wait up.'
『ねぇ、ピップ、待って！』
Not you too, Tom.
トム、君までかよ。
Come on, Wally.
行くよ、ウォリー。
The ravine.
たにぞこだ。
The ravine was filled with varieties of darkness.
たにぞこは色々なやみでみちていた。
Night, shadows, toad eyes and raven beaks.
夜、かげ、ヒキガエルの目、カラスのくちばし。
The ravine, the birth place of wild mushrooms.
たにぞこはやせいキノコのたんじょうちだ。
Pale toadstools, whispers and ripping's which call
あおじろいキノコ、ささやき、そしてさけびかける音が…
"Come, stay, linger and hide."
「来て、のこって、ゆっくりして、かくれて」
"Hide here forever. Never go."
「ここにえいえんにかくれろ。ぜったいに出て行かないで」
"Stay, stay."
「ここにとどまれ、とどまれ」
Huh?
あれっ？
Woo! Now, you know, I never believe in haunted houses.
うわっ！でもさ、幽霊やしきなんて信じたことないんだ。
'But that sure looks like one haunted house to me.'
『でも、あれはまちがえいなく幽霊やしきに見えるよ』
Ah, yes.
ああ、そうだね。
The house looked like it had been cut of black marble.
その家は黒いだいりせきで作られたみたいだった。
With many chimneys, the roof seemed a vast cemetery.
えんとつがたくさんあって、やねは広いはかばみたいだった。
Each flue signifying the burial place
それぞれのえんとつはまいそうばしょをしめしていて
of some old forgotten God of fire.
昔の忘れさられた火の神のはかだった。
'This is the best prank he's ever played.'
『これが彼がやった中で一番のいたずらだよ』
But it's not fair. He's gonna trick-or-treat ahead of us.
でもづるいだよ。みんなより先にトリック・オア・トリートしようとしてる。
Yeah, Pip always gets the most candy.
うん、ピップはいつも一番たくさんキャンディをもらう。
But that house is haunted.
でもあの家は幽霊が出るんだ。
Darn right, otherwise why would Pip lead us to it.
その通りだよ、でなきゃピップがそこに連れてくるりゆうがない。
Oh, yeah.
ああ、そうだね。
'Oh, my gosh.'
『なんてこった！』
This is no time to hold back, Tom. Remember?
今はえんりょできないよ、トム。覚えてる？
Ready, set, go!
よーい、スタート！
'Why, it's a Marley knocker.'
『なんでだろう、マーリーのノックだね』
You know, a Christmas Carol, Scrooge and Marley.
知ってるでしょ、クリスマスキャロルのスクルージとマーリー。
So, who's gonna knock?
で、だれがノックするの？
You!
君だ！
- Mm-hmm.
- Okay then, I'll do it.
- いやだ。
- じゃあ、私がやるね。
Oh, great, now you've done it, Jenny.
ああ、すごい、やっちゃったね、ジェニー。
'Enter.'
『入りなさい』
Oh, my gosh.
なんってこと！
Tom!
トム！
- Ah.
- Ooh.
Why have you disrupted me, and my business?
どうして私の仕事を邪魔したの？
- I...
- 私は…
Please, sir. Trick?
おねがいします、おじさん。トリック？
Or treat?
オア・トリート？
Oh, I really have no time for this.
あぁあ、本当に時間がないんだ。
'But sir, it's Halloween and--'
『でもおじさん、ハロウィンだし――』
So, you've tricked me? Is that it?
だから、私をだましたの？それだけ？
What would a treat be then, eh? Hm?
それなら、トリートは何になるんだろう？
Well, uh, we saw our friend coming here.
ええと、友達がここに来るのを見たんだ。
If you let him out, that'd be a treat.
もし彼を外に出すなら、それがトリートになるよ。
'Yeah.'
『うん。』
Who are you?
あなたはだれ？
I'm... name's Tom Skeleton.
僕は…トム・スケルトンだ。
Know why you're wearing bones, boy?
骨を身につけているりゆう、わかるかい？
Bah, didn't think so.
うん、そうは思わなかったね。
- And you?
- 君は？
- My friends call me--
- 友達は僕のことを…
Why so dressed up in an ancient mummy's rags? Hm?
なぜこだいミイラのほうたいを着ているんだ？ねぇ？
Time's up.
時間きれだ。
And you... the big one.
そして君…大きいやつ。
M-me sir?
私ですか？
Why a monster's face? Hm?
なぜモンスターの顔なの？
- And what about you, girl?
- それで、君はどうだい、女の子？
- Jenny.
- ジェニー。
Why are you wearing a costume of a witch? Hm?
なぜ魔女のいしょうを着ているの？ん？
No thoughts, eh?
考えはないの？
Oh, I'm wasting my breath.
ああ、なぜむだなことをいっている。
All dressed up for All Hallows' Eve.
ハロウィンのためにみんなは仮装してるんだね。
But you don't know why, or what or even from where.
でも君はなぜか、何か、どこから来たのかも知らないんだね。
- Pity.
- And you, sir?
- ざんねんだね。
- それで、あなたはどうですか、おじいさん？
Eh, who are you?
え、あなたは誰でしょうか？
Oh, yes, of course, hm, I beg your pardon.
あ、はい、もちろん、すみません。
Moundshroud is the name.
名前はマウンドシュラウドです。
'Carapace Clavicle Moundshroud.'
『カラパス・クラビクル・マウンドシュラウド』
'Is that not a fine name, children?'
『それはすばらしい名前じゃないかな、子どもたち？』
Does it... ring?
あれは…鳴る？
But I have work to do, tonight.
No treats... only trick.
でも今夜はやるべき仕事があるんだ。
トリートはなし…トリックだけだ。
So, if you'll excuse me.
それじゃ、失礼します。
'I'm on quite a tight schedule.'
『予定がとても詰まっているんだ』
Huh!
えっ！
Pip!
ピップ！
- You-you're a ghost!
- 'So, there you are.'
- あっあなたは幽霊だ！
- 『ああ、そこにいたんだ。』
Stop! We still have our appointment, you and I.
止まれ！まだよていがあるんだ、君と僕の。
Now, see what you've done.
ほらー、君がやったことを見てごらん。
- 'Pip.'
- 'Pipkin!'
- 『ピップ。』
- 『ピップキン！』
'Woo,　there must be a million of 'em.'
『うわ、きっと何百万もいるんだろう。』
'Pumpkins!'
『パンプキンだ！』
Look at 'em all.
ぜんぶ見てごらん。
A pumpkin tree.
パンプキンの木だ。
'No, a Halloween tree.'
『ちがう、ハロウィンの木だ。』
The pumpkins on the tree were not mere pumpkins.
木にぶら下がっているパンプキンはただのかぼちゃじゃなかった。
Each had a face sliced in it.
それぞれにかおがほられていた。
Each face was different.
それぞれのかおはみんなちがった。
Every nose was a weirder nose.
それぞれの鼻は先よりへんだった。
Every mouth smiled hideously in some new way.
口はみんな変に笑っていた。
A thousand grimaces and twice times
the thousand glares of fresh cut eyes.
千ものしかめっ面と、二千ばいに光るするどい目があった。
A thousand grimaces and twice times
the thousand glares of fresh cut eyes.
千ものしかめっ面と、二千ばいに光るするどい目があった。
Each blink held the remnant holiday spirit of years gone by.
まばたきするたびに、過ぎ去った年月のハロウィンののこりががあった。
Pipkin, where are you going?
ピップキン、どこへ行くの？
- We're over here.
- Why is he goin' up the tree?
- こっちだよ。
- なぜ彼は木に登っているの？
Uh.
'Oh, bother. Now, stay off of there!'
『ああ、めんどうだ。そこには近づかないで！』
Argh.
No, Pip, it's too high!
ダメだ、ピップ、高すぎる！
Come down from there! What are you...
そこから降りて！何を…
'Huh! Look!'
『えっ！見て！』
'That pumpkin!'
『あのパンプキン！』
'It looks just like, Pip.'
『ピップにそっくりだ。』
Argh!
Come on, we gotta help him.
さあ、たすけなきゃ。
Children, no.
子どもたち、だめだ。
No more interference.
もうじゃまするな。
Hold on, Pip, don't move.
待って、ピップ、うごかないで。
You've had your fun, boy.
Don't touch that.
楽しんだね、少年。
さわるな。
Got you.
つかまえた。
It belongs to me. Bring it here.
それは僕のものだ。ここに持ってきて。
Inexcusable. Inexcusable behavior!
ゆるせない。ゆるされない！
- Pip, Pip.
- Over here, Pip.
- ピップ、ピップ。
- こっちだ、ピップ。
- Hey, Pipkin.
- Oh, my gosh.
- やあ、ピップキン。
- うわっ。
Pip!
ピップ！
- He's melting.
- Where'd he go?
- 溶けてる。
- どこへ行ったの？
'Help me!'
『たすけて！』
No!
だめ！
Bother, bother, bother, I say.
めんどうだ、めんどうだ、めんどうだと言ってるよ。
'Do you've any idea what you've done?'
『やったこと、わかってるの？』
Now, my entire night's schedule is thrown off.
今夜のよていがぜんぶくるっちゃった。
What'd you do with Pip?
Where did you send him?
ピップに何したの？どこへ送ったの？
Oh, I didn't send him anywhere, skeleton.
いや、どこにも送ってないよ、スケルトン。
- Where is he?
- Yeah.
- 彼はどこ？
- どこ。
Oh, he must not have liked my company.
ああ、僕と一緒にいるのが好きじゃなかったんだね。
So, he escaped.
だから、にげたんだ。
Escaped, I might add, with a pumpkin that is my property.
にげたんだけど、僕のざいさんのパンプキンと一緒にね。
Well then, Cara-Clava...
じゃあ、カーラ‑クラバ…
Clavicle.
クラビクル。
But you may call me, Mr. Moundshroud.
でも、僕のことはミスター・マウンドシュラウドと呼べば良い。
Whatever your name is,
you bring him back right now.
名前はどうあれ、すぐに彼を戻してくれ。
'If only life were that easy. Hm.'
『人生がそんなに簡単だったらな。んー。』
By now, Pip's escaped
to the undiscovered country.
もうピップは未踏の国へにげたんだ。
No telling how long it will
take me to find him again.
また見つけるまでどれくらいかかるか、わからない。
Find him?
見つける？
Can we go with you?
We can help.
一緒に行ってもいい？ 手伝えるよ。
Impossible. You've helped quite enough already. Thank you.
無理だ。もう十分手伝ってくれたよ。ありがとう。
But anything's possible on Halloween, right?
でもハロウィンなら何でも起きるよね？
Ha! What do you know about Halloween?
はは！ハロウィンについて何か知ってるの？
'Four meddlers come barging into my house.'
『四人のおせっかいやきが家に乱入してくるんだ』
'Blundering into my business.'
『私の仕事にかってに入り込むんだ』
Not even knowing why.
なぜかすらわからない。
You are dressed as a skeleton, witch, mummy or..
君はスケルトン、魔女、ミイラ、あるいは…
Hm, wait a minute.
ん、ちょっと待って。
It is a long trip.
And it's hours before dawn.
長い旅になるよ。夜明けまでまだ何時間もある。
So, I've... we should have enough time.
だから、…時間は十分あるはずだ。
If we fly fast enough.
速く飛べればね。
Yes.
うん。
And far enough.
そして十分遠くまで。
Yes, yes.
はい、はい。
We might be able to catch Pipkin.
ピップキンをつかまえられるかも。
Grab his pumpkin fire soul and have a scavenger hunt as well.
彼のパンプキンの炎の魂を掴んで、宝探しもしよう。
'So you can find out who you are. What you are made of.'
『だから自分が何者か、何でできているかが分かるんだ』
And retrieve your Pipkin at the same time.
そして同時にピップキンを取り戻すんだ。
Well, will you come with me?
じゃあ、一緒に来てくれる？
And solve three mysteries in one?
そして一度に三つの謎を解くんだね？
Yes!
はい！
What fun then.
それで楽しいね。
The undiscovered country it is.
未踏の土地だよ。
Feast your eyes, a thousand Halloweens
目を見張れ、千のハロウィンが
wait out there to swallow us whole.
そこに待っていて、私たちを丸呑みする。
That barn, and on the sides of the barn
あの納屋と、納屋の側面
'the makings of an October Kite. You see?'
「10月のたこの作り方だよ、わかる？」
This way, skeleton.
This road, mummy.
こっちだ、スケルトン。この道はミイラだ。
'This fence, witch.
This meadow, monster.'
「このフェンス、魔女。この草原、モンスター。」
Do you see?
見える？
And they did see.
そして彼らは見た。
They saw the poster paper tapestry of circus beasts.
彼らはサーカスのけものたちがえがかれたポスターのかべかけを見た。
Pasted on the barn side years ago.
何年も前になやのそくめんにはられていた。
It was as if the captured animals
まるでつかまえられたどうぶつたちが
were waiting to be released.
はなたれるのを待っているかのようだった。
- Oh.
- あっ。
- Oh, my gosh.
- なんてこった！
Oh, my gosh.
なんてこった！
Let's build the kite then, shall we?
それじゃ、たこを作ろうか。
Time for you to help.
てつだう番だよ。
- Huh.
- えっ。
- Uh.
- うん。
They seized huge rows of animals
彼らは大量のどうぶつの列を
from the weathered walls.
風化した壁から奪い取った。
They tore off patches of fangs.
牙のかけらを引き裂いた。
Scripts of piercing eyes and sheets of claws and tails.
鋭い目と爪、尻尾の絵が走っていた。
The unshackled beasts cried.
解き放たれたけものたちが鳴き叫んだ。
And assembled in freed leaps and bounds.
そして自由に跳び回りながら集まった。
Oh, my gosh!
なんてこった！
- Will it fly us?
- I thought you'd never ask!
- 飛んでくれるかな？
- そんなこと聞くとは思わなかった！
'It won't fly straight.'
『まっすぐは飛ばないよ。』
A tail. We need a tail.
しっぽだ。しっぽが必要だ。
Right, boy.
そうだね、少年。
Who else for the tail?
しっぽは誰が欲しいの？
- I'm next.
- Not before me.
- 次は僕だ。
- 僕の前にはだめだ。
- Ah.
- あっ。
Fly.
飛べ。
'Fly!'
『飛べ！』
Ah, I just remembered
I hate heights.
ああ、思い出した。高い所が嫌いだ。
Two times two is four.
Four times four is sixteen.
2×2は4、4×4は16だ。
Sixteen times sixteen is..
16×16は…
256 is 65500..
256は65500…
It's Pip!
ピップだ！
Pip!
ピップ！
Seven hundred and forty.
七百四十。
Pip!
ピップ！
'Pipkin!'
『ピップキン！』
Where's he going?
彼はどこへ行くの？
Not where? When!
どこじゃなくて… いつ！
Four thousand, Halloweens ago.
四千年前のハロウィンだ。
Pipkin with my pumpkin has gone ahead.
僕のパンプキンを持ったピップキンは先に行ってしまった。
Or should I say, passed.
それとも、通り過ぎたと言うべきかな。
The moon began to blink, faster and faster
月がチラチラと光り始め、だんだん速くなった。
it began to wax to wane.
満ち欠けが繰り返し始まった。
Until a 1000 times over it flickered.
千回以上もちらつき続けた。
And then flickering changed the landscape below.
そしてそのちらつきが下の景色を変えた。
'Egypt.'
『エジプト』
'But it's brand new.'
『でも新しいんだ』
'That means we really have gotten back in time.'
『つまり、私たちは本当に時間をさかのぼったということだ』
Four thousand years.
四千年だ。
Hey.
ねえ。
O-oh, o-oh.
おっ、あっ。
Ar-are those real life ghosts?
あれは実際の幽霊なの？
They prefer being called spirits.
彼らは『スピリット』と呼ばれる方が好きだ。
- Tryin' to get into the houses?
- True.
- 家に入ろうとしてるの？
- 正解だよ。
And the food on the porches is for them?
ポーチの食べ物は彼らのためなの？
'Seems so.'
『そうみたいだ』
Why, it's good old-fashioned
trick-or-treat.
なぜだろう、昔ながらのトリック・オア・トリートだね。
- Four thousand years ago?
- Yes, imagine that.
- 四千年前ですか？
- はい、想像してみて。
Ah, look there.
あっ、あそこを見て。
'That ghost, uh, spirit.'
『あの幽霊、えっと、スピリットだ』
Sure, let's sneak up on him.
もちろん、こっそり近づこう。
'Pip.'
『ピップ』
'Hold on wait.'
『待って、ちょっと待って』
'Here we are.'
『ここに来たよ』
Enter. Sit. You're welcome.
入って。座って。どうぞう。
- Ah.
- Okay.
- あっ。
- オーケイ。
Ew!
きもっ！
- Ah!
- Uh.
- あっ！
- えっ。
Oh, my gosh.
なんてこった！
'Who's that?'
『あれは誰？』
Our great-grandfather.
Don't make a fuss.
私たちの曾祖父です。
騒がないで。
'He doesn't look very good.'
『彼はあまり元気そうに見えないね。』
Oh, he's been dead for 67 years.
ああ、彼は死んでから67年になるんだ。
So, what's he doing here?
それで、ここで何してるのかな？
Once a year, at the feast of the ghosts
年に一度、幽霊たちのごちそう祭りで
we invite him out to sit with us.
彼を招いて、一緒に座らせるんだ。
Eat.
食べよう。
Don't you wish we had a custom like this back home?
こんな風習が自分の家にもあったらいいなと思わない？
Dinner for the dead.
亡者の晩餐だ。
Ow!
痛っ！
Oh.
あっ。
What?
何？
Help!
たすけて！
Well, children. Seems we won't have time for dessert.
さあ、子どもたち。デザートの時間はもう残ってなさそうだね。
Come on, Mr. Moundshroud, he's getting too far ahead.
さあ、マウンドシュラウドさん、彼は前に行きすぎているよ。
Huh!
えっ！
The time is come. Hurry.
時間が来た。急いで。
Race, run.
レース、走れ。
Your three mysteries await.
あなたの三つの謎が待っている。
- Wow. Just look at these.
わぁ、これを見て。
- They're giants.
巨人だね。
Pip, didn't go in there, did he?
パイプ、そこに入らなかったよね？
Yes.
はい。
- Oh, great.
ああ、すごい。
- Go ahead, Tom.
トム、どうぞ。
- No, Ralph should go first.
いや、ラルフが先に行くべきだ。
- It's all yours, Wally.
ウォリー、全部君のものだよ。
No, you first. I insist.
いや、君が先だ。お願いだよ。
Betcha, Pip sent this out here to show us the way.
パイプが道を示すためにここへ送ってくれたんだよね。
It's got me！
つかまれた！
'Hold on.'
『待って。』
'We're coming after you.'
『私たちが後から来るよ。』
Wait up.
待って。
You, with the mummy wrappings and mummy face.
ミイラの巻き布と顔の君。
Who? Me?
誰？ 私？
Day is killed by night.
昼は夜に殺される。
Summer by winter.
夏は冬に取って代わられる。
'Osiris the sun God destroyed by his brother, darkness.'
『太陽神オサイリスは兄である闇に滅ぼされた。』
The seasons.
季節だ。
Is tha-that what the Egyptians thought of Halloween?
エジプト人はハロウィンをそんな風に考えていたの？
- You tell me.
- あなたが言って。
- Ah.
- ああ。
Why do you wear that costume?
なぜそのいしょうを着ているの？
'Oh, you're a mummy, boy.'
『おお、君はミイラだね、少年。』
'Because that's how Egyptians'
『それはエジプト人が…』
'dressed up their dead for eternity.'
『死者を永遠に装飾したからだ。』
Spun around in a cocoon of threads.
糸の繭に巻き付けられていた。
They hoped to come forth like fresh butterflies
彼らは新しい蝶のように生まれ変わることを願った
in some far dear-loving underworld.
遠く愛情深い冥界で。
Know your cocoon, boy.
Touch the strange stuffs.
自分の繭を知れ、少年。
不思議なものに触れろ。
Then, then every day was Halloween day then.
そうすれば、毎日がハロウィンの日になるんだ。
Yes, every day, Ralph.
Very good.
そうだ、毎日だ、ラルフ。
とても上手だ。
But, but what about Pipkin?
でも、でもパップキンは？
It may be too late.
遅すぎるかもしれない。
They are wrapping him up as a gift to eternity, now!
今すぐ彼を永遠への贈り物として包んでいるんだ！
You don't mean like, right now?
今すぐってこと？
Save them, Ralph.
ラルフ、たすけてあげて。
I'm coming, Pip.
行くよ、パップ。
'Ralph.'
『ラルフ。』
Pipkin?
ピップキン？
'Ralphy, is that you?'
『ラルフィー、それは君かい？』
Yeah, yeah it's me. I'm gonna get you out of here.
うん、うん、僕だよ。ここから連れ出すから。
'I'm fading.'
『消えていくんだ。』
No, you can't leave now. What about all our plans?
ダメだ、今は帰れないよ。計画はどうなるんだ？
You said someday you'd teach me
how to bat left-handed.
いつか左打ちを教えてくれるって言ってたね。
And you're the only friend
そして君だけが友達だ
who's never made fun
of my wearing glasses.
眼鏡をかけていることをからかわない唯一の友達だ。
'Learning to bat left-handed
isn't so hard, Ralphy.'
『左打ちを覚えるのはそんなに難しくないよ、ラルフィー。』
Oh, great. Now what do I do?
ああ、すごいね。次はどうすればいいの？
Come along, Pipkin.
You've had your fun.
さあ、ピップキン。一緒に来て。楽しかったね。
You and I have an appointment
to keep. You must keep it.
約束があるんだ、守らなきゃ。
No!
だめ！
Ah!
あっ！
The air vents. Come on.
通気口だ。行こう。
Yes. Find him. Catch him.
うん。見つけて。つかまえて。
Wait up, Ralph.
待って、ラルフ。
Hurry, but don't fall.
急いで、でも転ばないで。
- Oh, my gosh.
- Wally, don't jinx it, okay?
- ああ、なんてことだ。
- ウォリー、呪わないでね、いい？
Oh.
ああ。
'Pip!'
『ピップ！』
Hurry back.
Four corners, kids. Grab on.
早く戻って。四つの角だ、子どもたち。しっかり掴んで。
He can hide, but if we hurry,
we can go seek.
彼は隠れられるが、急げば探しに行ける。
Oh!
あっ！
Oh, my gosh, look down there.
うわっ、下を見て！
Wally, don't you dare tell
me how high we are.
ウォリー、絶対にどれくらい高いか教えないで。
Time to celebrate, children.
さあ、みんなでお祝いしよう。
'Happy New Year.'
『明けましておめでとう』
'No, it's Halloween.'
『いいえ、ハロウィンだ』
'Well,
maybe in our time it's All Hallows' Eve.'
『まあ、私たちの時代ではハロウィン前夜かもしれない。』
'But in this time,
it's New Year's Eve.'
『でもこの時代では大晦日だ。』
'The true end of summer,
and cold start of winter.'
『本当の夏の終わり、そして寒い冬の始まりだ。』
'Happy New Year.'
『明けましておめでとう』
Down in the crowd.
Is that him below?
群衆の中で。下にいるのは彼かな？
No, he's there above.
いいえ、彼は上にいる。
What is this place?
ここは何だ？
Where are we?
私たちはどこにいるの？
When are we?
私たちはいつなの？
It's olden times, children.
Ancient times. Stonehenge.
古代の時代だ、子どもたち。ストーンヘンジだ。
You need courage tonight.
今夜は勇気が必要だ。
It's the Dark Ages, and this is the longest
It's the darkest night in all dark time.
暗黒時代だ、そしてこれは最も長く、最も暗い夜だ。
darkest night in all dark time.
全ての暗闇の中で最も暗い夜だ。
- Oh, my gosh.
- ああ、なんてことだ。
- What? What?
- 何だって？ 何だって？
Is that you, Pip?
それは君か、ピップ？
'In these dark times, people thought'
『この暗い時代には、人々は考えていた』
'that on this special night'
『この特別な夜に』
'those who had died during the
year were turned into beasts.'
『一年間に死んだ者はけものに変えられた』
'Became animals.'
『どうぶつになった』
Dogs, wild boars or worst of all... cats.
犬、野豚、そして最悪は…猫だ。
'Black as bad luck. Black as sin.'
『不運のように黒く、罪のように黒い』
Pip?
ピップ？
'Black as night.'
『夜のように黒い。』
Easy, pip. Steady, boy.
落ち着いて、ピップ。よし、よし。
We-we, we'll save you.
私たちが、たすけに行くよ。
No, I'll get him.
いや、俺が連れてくる。
Come here, Pip.
こっちに来て、ピップ。
Pip. No, come back.
ピップ。いや、戻って！
Tom, I-I think this is the last year
トム、これが最後の年だと思う
ever go trick-or-treat with you guys. Okay?
みんなとトリック・オア・トリートできるのはね。いい？
Peek-a-boo.
来たぞ！
There was a hustle of brooms in the broom works.
ほうき工場でほうきがざわざわしていた。
An immense traffic jams of brooms for witches
魔女たちのためのほうきが大渋滞。
to perch upon.
止まるばしょがなく。
It was as if all earth's forests gave up their branches
まるで地球の森が枝をすべて手放したかのように
in one broom and fling.
一本のほうきに集めて投げた。
And scouring autumn fields cut clean and throttled tight
秋の畑をきれいに刈り取り、しっかり締めた
such cereal grains
穀物を
as made good sweepers, thrashers, and beaters.
掃除用、たたき用、叩き用に作った。
Hey, you know what that is? A Broom Festival.
ねえ、あれが何か分かる？ほうき祭りだよ。
And they're making brooms. But not ordinary brooms.
みんなでほうきを作ってる。でも普通のほうきじゃない。
Touch them.
触ってみて。
Feel them.
感触を確かめて。
Broomsticks for witches.
魔女用のほうき棒。
For you.
君のために。
Me?
私に？
Whoops!
おっとっとっ。
Ah.
あっ。
Ride him, Jenny.
乗ってみて、ジェニー。
Anyone else care to try it?
他にやってみたい子は？
- Whoa.
- わぁ。
- Whoa!
- わぁ！
Oh, my gosh. Oh, my gosh.
Oh, my gosh!
ああ、なんてことだ。ああ、なんてこった！
Jenny, listen to me.
ジェニー、聞いて。
No, I wanna be back on the ground!
いや、地面に戻りたい！
Just put me back on the ground!
すぐに地面に戻して！
'Where's your spirit of adventure?'
『冒険心はどこへ行ったんだ？』
Witches have nothing to fear from their brooms.
魔女はほうきから何も恐れることはない。
Betcha, it's no different from riding your bike!
ほら、バイクに乗るのと同じだよ！
My bike, like my bike.
私のバイク、バイクと同じだ。
Hey, you're right!
ねぇ、正しいよ！
Now, how about follow the leader?
さあ、リーダーについて来ようか？
Look!
見て！
I can't believe it.
While flying, I saw, I saw...
信じられない。飛びながら、見たんだ、見た…
Pip! Was it Pip?
ピップ！ ピップだったの？
No. Witches! Everywhere!
違う。魔女だ！ どこでも！
Of course. It can't be Halloween without witches!
もちろん、魔女なしでハロウィンはあり得ない！
- Then they really were witches?
- じゃあ本当に魔女だったの？
- Well, yes and no.
- うん、でもそうでもない。
- Could they fly broomsticks?
- Not really.
- ほうきで空を飛べたのか？
- そんなことはない。
- They could talk to the dead?
- Nope.
- 死者と話せたのか？
- いや。
Make hairy warts grow on people?
人に毛むくろを生やす？
Sorry, no.
ごめん、ない。
Make people jump by sticking pins in dolls?
人形に針を刺して人を跳ねさせる？
Not to my knowledge.
知らない。
Well, heck then, what could they do?
じゃあ、何ができたんだ？
Nothing.
何もできない。
Nothing?
何も？
'Ah, plenty claimed they could.'
『ああ、できると言う人はたくさんいた。』
But that was just a means to protect their privacy.
しかしそれはただ、プライバシーを守る手段だった。
Ever wondered what the word 'witch' really means?
「魔女」という言葉の本当の意味を考えたことは？
Well, no... Not until tonight.
ううん… 今夜まで。
Ha ha ha!
ははは！
Wished that information.
その情報が欲しかった。
In the Dark Ages anyone with half a brain, any knowledge
暗黒時代では、少しでも頭が良く、知識がある者は
had his wits about him. Yes.
常に警戒していた。そうだ。
So, anyone too smart was called...
だから、賢すぎる者は…
A witch!
魔女と呼ばれた！
Exactly.
その通り。
And the really smart ones,
ones with the wits called it
さらに本当に賢い者は、
知恵を持つ者はそれを
Magic. Magic!
魔法と呼んだ。魔法！
In every town, in every tiny village
どの町でも、小さな村でも
the old religions hid out.
古い宗教は潜んでいた。
And all the little lollygagging cults
そして、すべての小さなだらだらしたカルトは
all flavors and types scrambled to survive.
様々な形態で必死に生き延びようとしていた。
By every crossroad and by every haystack
すべての交差点と干し草の山で
dark forms jumped across flames
暗い姿が炎を越えて跳んだ
as fires burned everywhere.
火が至る所で燃えていた。
'In the end all Europe was a cloud of witches' smoke.'
『結局ヨーロッパ全体が魔女の煙の雲だった。』
Anyone want to be a witch?
誰か魔女になりたい？
No, no, not me!
いや、いや、けっこうだ！
'Pip!'
『ピップ！』
Wonderful, let's play tag.
すばらしいね、鬼ごっこしよう。
Now, Pip, the pumpkin doesn't belong to you anymore.
ねえ、ピップ、パンプキンはもう君のものじゃないよ。
Hold on, Pip!
待って、ピップ！
Grab on!
しっかりつかんで！
Hurray! Let's show 'em, Jenny.
やった！見せてやろう、ジェニー。
Some switch, huh, Jenny?
You saving me, huh?
ちょっと変わったね、ジェニー？
たすけてくれるんだね？
Don't fall, Pip!
落ちないで、ピップ！
What if I need you to talk me
down out of an apple tree again?
またリンゴの木から降りるとき、君に声をかけてもらう必要があったら？
Tighter, Pip. If I ever lost you...
もっとしっかり、ピップ。もし君を失ったら…
Hey, no tears. Wouldn't you just hate to have Tom see you cry?
泣かないで。トムに泣く姿を見られたくないでしょ？
- Yeah. Fun and games are over.
- うん。遊びは終わりだ。
- No, they're not.
- いや、まだ続くよ。
Follow me if you can. Ready, set, go!
できるならついてきて。よーい、スタート！
There's got to be two zillion, ten billion acres of air
二千兆、百億エーカーもの空気が
wrapped round the world.
世界を包んでいるはずだ。
Which half-acre is he headed for?
彼はどの半エーカーへ向かうのだろう？
- Now, what?
- 今、何だって？
- I'm still a witch, right?
- まだ魔女だよね？
I got the wits, follow me!
頭はある、ついて来て！
You heard her! Let's go.
彼女の言うこと聞いたでしょ！ 行こう。
There! There he is!
そこだ！ 彼がいる！
Well, is he here?
さて、彼はここにいるのか？
Gotta be. I can feel him in my bones.
いるはずだ。骨の奥まで感じる。
Where is he, Mr. Moundshroud?
どこにいるんだ、マウンドシュラウドさん？
Where, you may ask? Hm...
どこかって？ ふむ…
Why, hiding out.
なぜなら、隠れているから。
Protecting his pumpkin soul.
パンプキンの魂を守っているんだ。
How observant of you, skeleton.
観察力があるね、がいこつさん。
But to be precise, it is my pumpkin!
でも正確に言うと、あれは僕のパンプキンだ！
Come out, come out, wherever you are.
出ておいで、どこにいても。
I have a riddle for you, monster.
謎かけがあるよ、モンスター。
- Can't you ask someone else?
- 他の人に聞いてくれないの？
- No, no, it's your turn now.
- いやいや、今度は君の番だ。
What's bigger and stronger than demons and witches?
悪魔や魔女よりも大きくて強いものは何だ？
A place so big, it holds back the night and nightmares?
夜とあくむを押し返すほど広いばしょは？
What's bigger than devils and ghosts?
悪魔や幽霊よりも大きいものは？
Bigger?
もっと大きい？
もっと？
Ah...
ああ…
- A cathedral?
- Well done, monster.
- 大聖堂か？
- よくやった、モンスター。
Yes. Places where a running and renegade child
はい。走り回る反逆の子どもが
can hide and take sanctuary.
隠れて安全に過ごせるばしょです。
Sanctuary. Sanctuary! Sanctuary!
せいいきだ。せいいき！ せいいき！
'Sanctuary!'
『せいいき！』
- 'Help!'
- Pip!
- 『たすけて！』
- ピップ！
Ralph, Wally, Jenny.
ラルフ、ウォリー、ジェニー。
I think we're getting warmer!
だんだん近づいてきた気がする！
Something wrong, Mr. Moundshroud?
何かもんだいですか、マウンドシュラウドさん？
Yeah, you took half the night to catch Pip.
うん、ピップをつかまえるのに夜の半分かかったね。
So how come you're not going up to get him?
それなのに、どうして上に行かないの？
Well, simply because, there are some places
実はね、ある場所があるからだ
where I'm not as welcome as others.
そこでは他のところほど歓迎されないんだ。
Ah, why don't you collect Pip for me?
ああ、ピップを取ってくれない？
Please... Wally...
お願い… ウォリー…
But how do we reach him?
でも、どうやって彼に届くの？
There are ways. After all,
tonight of all nights is still...
方法はあるよ。だって、今夜は特別な夜だ…
- Halloween!
- Precisely.
- ハロウィンだ！
- その通り。
So why not finish building the cathedral, with your feet?
足で大聖堂を完成させたらどう？
Are you kidding?
冗談でしょ？
No, call the stones with your feet.
いや、足で石を呼び寄せるんだ。
You coming, Mr. Moundshroud?
来るのか、マウンドシュラウドさん？
Ha ha ha, you know I'm always with you.
ははは、いつでも一緒だよ。
Carry on.
続けて。
Come on, guys! Pip is counting on us.
さあ、みんな！ピップが頼ってるよ。
Leap? Run! They will follow.
跳べ！走れ！追いかけてくるよ。
Oh!
あっ！
Step lightly.
軽く踏んで。
- Sorry, Wally.
- ごめん、ウォリー。
- Ah.
- ああ。
- Oh!
- おっ！
- Bravo.
- すごい。
They ran on pure, windy light, only to have bricks, and stones
純粋で風のような光の上を走ったら、レンガと石が
and mortar shuffle like cards,
モルタルがカードのように混ざり合い、
and take form beneath their toes and heels.
足の裏で形を作り始めた。
Oh, enough.
もう、いい加減にして。
There, much better, much better.
そこだ、ずっと良くなったね。
Notre Dame, I think we've built Notre Dame!
ノートルダムだ、作ったみたいだね。
- But this can't be Notre Dame.
- でもこれがノートルダムじゃないよね。
- Why not?
- どうして？
Can't you see what's missing?
何が足りないか見えないの？
- Monster faces.
- 怪物の顔。
- You know, stone devils.
- 石の悪魔だよ。
Marble demons.
大理石の悪魔。
'Gargoyles.'
『ガーゴイル。』
Ever wonder why we like dressing up
as monsters, beasts, and ornery critters?
なぜ怪物やけもの、やんちゃな生き物に仮装するのが好きなのか、考えたことある？
Monsters remind us of all the dark nights
and all fears and nightmares.
『怪物は暗い夜と、すべての恐怖やあくむを思い出させてくれる。』
Go ahead, monster. They're waiting for your summons.
さあ、モンスター、君の呼びかけをみんなが待っているよ。
The unemployed of all midnight Europe
shivered in their stone sleep. And came awake.
真夜中のヨーロッパで働かない者たちが、石の眠りの中で震え、目を覚ました。
All the old beasts, all the old tales
and unused demons put by, reared at the whistle
古いけものや昔話、使われていない悪魔たちが笛の音で起き上がり
and in spectral dust devils of propulsion, arrived.
そして幽霊のような砂ぼこりの渦で現れた。
'Monster, there's your carved stone quarry.'
『モンスター、彫られた石の採石場だよ。』
Gargoyles, now the building is finished, Tom.
ガーゴイル、建物が完成したよ、トム。
'Tom, Jenny, Ralph, Wally, are you here?'
『トム、ジェニー、ラルフ、ウォリー、みんなどこにいるの？』
Where are you, Pip?
ピップ、どこにいるの？
'Here.'
『ここだ。』
Oh, my gosh!
ああ、なんてことだ！
'Ge-get me, get me out of here.'
『たすけて、ここから出して！』
- I'm scared.
- It's Gargoyle language?
- 怖いよ。
- ガーゴイル語？
He can talk when the rain comes out of his mouth...
雨が口から出るとき、彼は話すことができる…
Or the wind blows over his teeth!
それとも風が歯の上を吹くときだ！
Come on, just a little bit higher.
さあ、もう少しだけ高く。
You can do it!
できるよ！
No cutting in line, plenty for all. One at a time.
列を抜かさないで、みんな分け前はたっぷり。順番にね。
Hold it. I'm the only live Gargoyle here!
待って。ここにいる唯一の生きたガーゴイルは僕だけだ！
- Right, Mr. Moundshroud?
- そうですね、マウンドシュラウドさん？
- Indeed.
- 確かに。
So, it's up to me.
だから、任せてくれ。
Tom, right.
Rob, left!
トムは右へ。
ロブは左へ！
Together now!
さあ、一緒に！
Whoa!
うわっ！
Oh, Pipkin, what's happened to you?
ああ、ピップキン、どうしたんだ？
- I think I'm dying.
- 死にそうだ。
- You are not!
- そんなことない！
You tried, Wally. All of you did.
頑張ったね、ウォリー。みんながやったんだ。
Shut up! Shut up, will you?
黙って！ 黙ってくれる？
Don't quit, keep running, escape, we'll follow.
やめないで、走り続けて、にげて、僕らが追うから。
- Gotta go now, Wally.
- 今すぐ行かないと、ウォリー。
- No, no, Pip, you can't!
- ダメだ、ダメだ、ピップ、無理だよ！
Wait, will you?
待ってくれる？
Remember that time, those fireworks
あの時の花火のこと覚えてる？
I stored in my bedroom.
僕の部屋にしまってたんだ。
The one's who started the fire.
火事を起こしたのはあいつだ。
Uh, sure smoked up your house.
うん、確かに家が煙だらけになったね。
An‑and you took the blame for me!
それで君が僕のせいにされたんだ！
I never thanked you for that.
ずっとありがとうって言えてなかった。
Oh!
あっ！
Wally. Come on, two points.
Toss it right up here.
ウォリー、さあ、二つポイントだ。
ここに投げて。
- Goodbye, Wally.
- No, Pip, I won't let you go!
- さようなら、ウォリー。
- ダメ、ピップ、君を離さない！
No!
だめ！
Ah!
ああ！
'That's it! Get the pumpkin.'
『それだ！パンプキンを取れ。』
Oh.
おお。
No!
だめ！
I'm coming, Pip!
『来るよ、ピップ！』
Come on, we can't loose him now!
さあ、今さら彼を失うわけにはいかない！
There's no escape.
にげ道はない。
I'll chalk his course to a final graveyard.
彼の行き先をさいごのぼちに書き込んでおく。
'Well, we've arrived children.'
『さあ、みんなついたよ。』
'Our final destination.'
『我々の最終の目的地だ。』
But where are we?
でも、ここはどこだ？
Listen, guitars!
聞いて、ギター！
And those must be skeleton bones.
それに、あれはがいこつの骨だろう。
No, marimbas and xylophones.
いや、マリンバとシロフォンだ。
Castanets.
カスタネット。
'Hooray!'
『やったー！』
That sounds like a bon fire!
焚き火の音みたいだ！
'Mexico!'
『メキシコ！』
'Look, all the graveyards!'
『見て、ぼちがいっぱいだ！』
'Where are all those people going?'
『あの人たちはどこへ行くんだろう？』
El Dia de los Muertos.
死者の日（エル・ディア・デ・ロス・ムエルトス）。
The Day of the Dead.
死者の日。
Back home, we'd never think going to a graveyard
ハロウィンに墓地へ行くなんて、家では決して考えない。
on Halloween.
ハロウィンのことだ。
But this looks like fun!
でも、これは楽しそうだ！
Yeah! Alright!
うん！よし！
'Look at little funerals for sale!'
『売られている小さな葬式を見て！』
Are those real coffins?
それは本物のかんおけ？
- Hey! Look!
- ねえ！見て！
- What's this?
- これは何？
Whoa! The newspapers are full of bones!
うわっ！新聞が骨でいっぱいだ！
Mexican Halloween's are sure better than ours.
メキシコのハロウィンは確かにうちのよりいいね。
ｎ
Huh! Pipkin! He must be around here someplace.
あれ？ピップキン！どこかにいるはずだ。
Oh... Ah!
あっ… ああ！
Oh!
あっ！
O-oh!
おっ、あっ！
Sweet skulls!
甘いドクロ！
- Crystal sugar candy skulls!
- クリスタルシュガーのキャンディドクロ！
- Oh! What's going on?
- あれ？何が起きてるの？
'Sweet skulls! Sweet skulls. Crystal sugar candy skulls.'
『甘いドクロ！甘いドクロ。クリスタルシュガーのキャンディドクロ。』
'Hey, look at the candy heads.'
『ねえ、キャンディの頭を見て！』
Tell me your name, I give you your skull.
名前を言って、ドクロをあげるよ。
Tom!
トム！
How about Ralph? Ha ha!
ラルフは？はは！
- Um, um, Wally!
- あの、ウォリー！
- Ha ha ha, Jenny!
- ははは、ジェニー！
Oh!
あっ！
Ha ha ha.
ははは。
Hold them in your palms.
手のひらに乗せて。
Bite it, swallow it and survive.
噛んで飲み込んで、生き残ろう。
Come out the far black tunnel of Halloween
ハロウィンの遠い黒いトンネルから出て
and be glad, oh, so glad you are alive! Ha ha ha.
そして嬉しく思って、命があることに感謝しよう！ははは。
Hey, we better look for Pip now, it's getting late.
ねえ、もう遅くなるからピップを探そう。
Yes! For All Hallows' Eve its to be away. Head's up!
うん！万聖節のために外へ行くんだ。気をつけて！
Hey! What's goin' on?
ねえ！何が起きてるの？
Whoa! Whoa!
うわっ！うわっ！
- Ooh.
- あっ。
- Ah.
- おっ。
- That was fun.
- 楽しかったね。
- What's next?
- 次は何？
No more time for games, children.
もう遊ぶ時間はないよ、子どもたち。
The night ends here.
夜はここで終わる。
Do-down in that hole?
あの穴の中にいるのかい？
Down in the catacombs, he's waiting.
地下の地下墓地で、彼は待っている。
Simon says, "Bring him up."
サイモンが言う。「上げてこい」。
And be extra careful with my pumpkin.
僕のパンプキンは特に慎重に扱って。
We'll bring him up but we'll keep him for ourselves.
持ち上げるけど、私たちだけで残すんだ。
Bravely spoken.
よく言ったな。
Pip would have liked that.
ピップは喜んだだろう。
Hurry the dawn is approaching.
急げ、夜明けが近づいている。
'Mummy's.'
『ミイラたち。』
Their families couldn't pay the rent on their graves.
彼らのかぞくははかのいじひを払えなかった。
So the grave digger put them down here.
だからはかほり人がここに埋めたんだ。
A little too dry for me.
ちょっと乾きすぎるな。
Shh.
シッ。
What're you doing there, Pip?
そこでは何してるんだ、ピップ？
I have to stay.
ここに居なきゃいけない。
I'm trapped.
閉じ込められた。
But if you stay there you'll stay forever.
そこにずっといると、永遠にそこに留まることになる。
Tourist will buy tickets to come look at you.
観光客がチケットを買って、君を見るために来るだろう。
Pip, come on out it's just us.
ピップ、出てきて。ここには僕たちだけだ。
Huh.
え？
'Oh, my gosh.'
『ああ、なんてこった！』
They're alive.
彼らは生きている。
- What do we do?
- I don't know.
- どうすればいいの？
- わからない。
Tell me, why do you wear bones skeleton?
教えて、なぜがいこつを身につけているの？
Because of my name.
名前のせいだ。
Oh, have you learnt nothing tonight, boy.
ああ、今夜は何も学んでいないのかい、少年。
Because maybe if we face death eye ball to eye ball
死と目と目を合わせて向き合えば
it loses its power over us, it can't scare us.
その力は弱まり、怖がらせられなくなるかもしれない。
Excellent, Tom.
素晴らしい、トム。
So I've got to save, Pip. Alone.
だから、ピップを救わなきゃいけないんだ。一人で。
Ah.
ああ。
'You can do it.'
『君ならできるよ。』
'Don't look back! Don't look back!'
『振り向くな！ 振り向くな！』
'Just go straight!'
『まっすぐ進め！』
Woo! Woo! Woo!
うぉー！ うぉー！ うぉー！
Oh, Pip, don't die. I'm sorry. So sorry.
ピップ、死なないで。ごめん。本当にごめん。
What do you mean, Tom?
どういうことだ、トム？
You came through.
君は通り抜けたんだ。
No, all this tonight is my fault.
いや、今夜のすべては僕のせいだ。
I once wished for something to happen to you so I could be leader for a change.
かつて君に何か起きてほしいと願ったんだ、リーダーになるチャンスを得るために。
But I never thought something like appendicitis.
でも盲腸炎みたいなことになるとは思わなかった。
Ah, don't be silly, Tom.
I'll let you lead anytime.
あはは、馬鹿にしないで、トム。
いつでもリーダーにさせてあげるよ。
Huh? What's happening?
えっ？ 何が起きてるの？
Pip! No!
ピップ！ ダメだ！
Ha ha ha! This truly has been fun, hasn't it?
ははは！ 本当に楽しかったね、そうだよね？
And I know just where I'm going to hang this.
そして、これをどこに掛けるか、ちゃんとわかってるよ。
No! I got to him first. I won.
だめだ！ 先に取ったんだ。勝ったよ。
Sorry, this never was a contest.
ごめん、これは競争じゃなかったんだ。
It's rent was past due,
it's simple and plain.
家賃が滞納してたんだ、シンプルにね。
- That's not fair.
- You cheated!
- 不公平だよ。
- あなたがズルした！
You said if we came with you
and solve the mysteries
君が言った、もし僕たちが一緒に来て
謎を解けば
of Halloween, we could save Pipkin.
ハロウィンの謎を解けば、ピップキンを救えると。
Children, it's business.
子どもたち、これは仕事だ。
With his illness, his rent came due
彼の病気で、家賃が払えなくなった
and there was no payment.
そして支払いはできなかった。
彼は僕のものだ！
- Well, we tried.
- We did our best.
- うん、頑張ったよ。
- 最善を尽くしたんだ。
Let's go home.
帰ろう。
No! Wait!
『待って！』
Mr. Moundshroud, I'll make his payment for him.
『マウンドシュラウドさん、彼の代わりに支払います。』
You? What could you possibly
have to pay with?
『君が？ 何で支払えるんだ？』
Money?
『金か？』
Currency?
『通貨か？』
Coin of the realm?
『王国の硬貨か？』
What if uh...
『もし…』
'What if what, boy?'
『何が何だ、少年？』
Well, what if I gave you, uh, something of value.
『まあ、もし君に価値あるものをあげたらどうだ？』
Say, A year of my life.
『例えば、僕の人生の一年間をさ。』
Oh!
『あっ！』
You'd do that for him?
『それを彼のためにやるのか？』
Yes. A year from the end of my life.
『はい。僕の人生の最後から一年間です。』
It's yours if it would save Pip.
それがピップを救えるなら君のものだ。
One precious year from the far burned out candle end
遠くで灯が切れた先からの貴重な一年間。
of your life, eh?
君の人生の、ね？
Think before you answer!
答える前に考えて！
You won't miss it now, but 60 years from today
今は気づかないかもしれないが、
今日から60年後に
to 72 or 80 when I come for payment, you may regret it.
72歳か80歳で支払いに来たとき、
後悔するかもしれない。
Is he worth it, this friend of yours, hm?
この友達はそれだけの価値があるのか、うん？
More than you'll ever know.
君が思う以上だ。
Hm. One boy's love.
うん。一人の少年の愛だ。
'Take one of mine too.'
『私のものも一つ取って。』
- And mine.
- I'm in.
- それも私の分だ。
- 私も参加する。
Four for one makes good business, doesn't it?
一つで四つ、うまい商売だよね？
Yes! I like it!
はい！ 気に入った！
Here then!
それじゃ、こちら！
Chew, swallow, swallow and chew.
噛んで、飲んで、飲んで、また噛んで。
- Pip!
- Wait!
『ピップ！』
『待って！』
Come back!
戻って！
Where's he going?
彼はどこへ行くの？
After all this, only one place.
これだけしたら、たった一つのばしょだけだ。
Home!
家だ！
But we saved him, didn't we?
でも私たちは彼を助けたよね、そうだよね？
Will he live, Mr. Moundshroud?
彼は生き残れるかな、マウンドシュラウドさん？
Come! Our night journey is over!
来なさい！ 夜の旅は終わったんだ！
One last game of musical chairs!
最後の椅子取りゲームだ！
Moundshroud sprung about like a whirlwind.
マウンドシュラウドは竜巻のように跳ね回った。
His arms flung out, cut the air in slicing
彼の腕は伸び、空気を切るように
grabs and swoops
つかんで、すくい上げた
that shook the mummies in earthquakes of bones.
骨の地震でミイラを揺らした。
Fall down, whistled the whirlwind.
「倒れろ」と竜巻が笛のように鳴った。
Fall up, was the echo.
「上へ倒れろ」がエコーした。
They tumbled through the sky like a self made storm.
自分で作った嵐のように空を転がり落ちた。
It was the end of their 4000 year flight.
それは4000年の旅の終わりだった。
From Egyptian crypts.
エジプトの墓から。
To English broom fields.
イギリスのほうき畑へ。
To French quarry works.
フランスの採石場へ。
To Mexican bone yards.
メキシコの骨置き場へ。
They swooped homeward.
彼らは家へと舞い戻った。
Once around the court house.
裁判所の周りを一回回った。
And twice around the pumpkin burning tree.
パンプキンの燃える木の周りを二回回った。
And a final time around old Moundshroud's house.
最後にマウンドシュラウドの古い家の周りを回った。
Where dust sifted out windows to greet them.
窓から埃が舞い上がり、彼らを迎えた。
And that, children is Halloween!
それが、子どもたち、ハロウィンだ！
All rolled up in one.
すべてがひとつにまとめられた。
Night and day. Summer and winter.
昼と夜。夏と冬。
Life and death.
生と死。
Four thousand years ago, 100 years or this year.
四千年前でも、百年前でも、今年でも。
'One place or another.'
『どこかのばしょで。』
'The celebrations are all the same.'
『お祭りはみんな同じだ。』
El Dia de los Muertos.
エル・ディア・デ・ロス・ムエルトス。
Day of the Dead.
死者の日。
Feast of ghosts.
幽霊のごちそう祭り。
All Hallows' Eve.
オールホーリーズ・イブ。
Halloween!
ハロウィン！
I thank you for a most amusing and profitable evening.
楽しくて有意義な夜を過ごさせてくれてありがとう。
And after what you've done for your friend.
そして、友だちのためにしてくれたことに感謝します。
One I will never forget.
忘れられない出来事だ。
- But what about--
- でも、どうしたんだ――
- Run!
- 走れ！
See for yourselves!
自分の目で確かめて！
The last grand trick-or-treat!
最後の壮大なトリック・オア・トリートだ！
'Look! It's his pumpkin.'
『見て！ それは彼のパンプキンだ。』
'Oh, my gosh! He must be okay.'
『ああ、なんてことだ！ 彼は大丈夫だろう。』
Hi, guys.
やあ、みんな。
- Pipkin!
- ピップキン！
- You are alive!
- 君は生きてるんだ！
Hooray!
やった！
They took my appendix out.
盲腸を取ってもらった。
For a while, I thought I was a goner.
しばらくは死んだと思った。
Imagine that.
想像してみて。
Anyway, thanks for... everything.
とにかく、全部ありがとう。
Huh? What are you talking about? We didn't do anything.
え？何を言ってるんだ？僕たちは何もしてないよ。
- Nothing.
- 何も。
- Heck.
- まったく。
Gosh.
やれやれ。
Is that so?
そうなの？
Well, I had dreams about Pyramids, Stonehenge
うん、ピラミッドやストーンヘンジの夢を見たんだ
Paris and Mexico.
パリとメキシコだ。
Like I said, thanks.
言った通り、ありがとう。
Then a great, wondrous, happy, tiredness gathered
それから、素晴らしく、おどろくほどの、幸せな疲れが
in their eyelids and arms and feet.
まぶたや腕や足に集まった。
The witch and mummy and monster and skeleton
魔女とミイラと怪物と骸骨が
ran back to their own houses to remember this special night
この特別な夜を思い出すために自分の家へ走り戻った
that they would never in all their lives, ever forget.
それは彼らの生涯で決して忘れられないものとなった。
Old Moundshroud blew out one last candle.
古いマウンドシュラウドが最後のろうそくを吹き消した。
Causing it to flicker and flare.
それがちらつき、燃え上がった。
The wind blew in and out the fresh cut mouth
風が新しく切られた口に吹き込み、抜いた。
with the whispered song.
ささやく歌と共に。
A 1000 pumpkins were seized and blown into the sky.
千個のパンプキンが捕らえられ、空へと吹き上げられた。
That is all but one pumpkin.
それはすべて、ただ一つのパンプキンを除いて。
Pip's pumpkin.
ピップのパンプキン。
Pip's spirit and soul.
ピップの魂と精神。
That was traded for and saved on that Halloween night
それはハロウィンの夜に交換され、救われた。
So long ago.
ずっと昔のことだ。